Guide to the Eero Saarinen Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Project Records, 1936-1989; 1942-1962; Series IV
  - Job 5603: Trans World Flight Center [aka TWA Terminal 5], Idlewild [now John F. Kennedy] Airport, New York, NY
    With a central vaulted structure flanked by two wings, check-in facilities and a the baggage claim area, Saarinen designed the space to accommodate the deposit of departing passengers' baggage at the check-in counter and the retrieval of arriving passengers' baggage from revolving carousels located near ground transportation. Two 125-foot-long tubular passageways led from the main terminal complex to podlike boarding areas, referred to as "departure stations," which constituted another innovation in airport design. The boarding areas' remote locations increased the terminal's perimeter and allowed fourteen jets to dock simultaneously. Warren Platner was largely responsible for the interior design. The building program called for five dining facilities, but the Saarinen firm was commissioned to design only the Ambassador Club, which it furnished with Pedestal tables and molded seating.
    Grove, Shepherd, Wilson, and Kruge, contractors, oversaw the building's construction. The concrete for each shell was poured in a single uninterrupted session; the side shells each required thirty hours. The project team included the structural engineering firm of Ammann and Whitney, with the firm's engineer Abba Tor playing a key role; Jaros, Baum, and Bolles, mechanical engineers; Bolt, Beranek, and Newman, acoustic consultants; and Stanley McCandless, lighting consultant. From the Saarinen office, Kevin Roche, Norman Pettula, Cesar Pelli, and Edward Saad were key collaborators on the design. The terminal is currently being reconfigured for passengers after many years of disuse and threats of demolition.
    Documentation for the TWA Terminal is extensive, and includes several rolls of detailed architectural and structural working drawings showing how Saarinen calculated all of the curves in the building. A total of 40 rolls of drawings exist for this project, many of those for the Intermediate Stage Ramp House. Job numbers 6210, 6302, 6307 all pertain to the intermediate stage ramp house, an alteration commissioned after Saarinen's death. There are a large number of oversize drawings on board, primarily sepias, showing baggage loading diagrams and loading/unloading zones. Photographic documentation is also extensive. Of particular note are the light studies of the model taken by Baltazar Korab and the interior photographs made by Charles Eames.
    - Clippings, 1957-1978 (Box 269, Folder 898 - 900)
      - Additional material (Box 672, Folder 27)
    - Clippings, 1961-1967, 1986, undated (Box 273, Folder 901 - 903)
      - Additional material (Box 672, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence: publicity and press, 1956-1962 (Box 273, Folder 904 - 908)
    - Drawings
      - As-built unit terminal building
        - Architectural originals, undated (Box 274–280)
        - Electrical sepias; electrical shop drawings, undated (Box 281)
        - Heating, ventilating & air-conditioning sepias, undated (Box 282)
        - Structural sepias, undated (Box 283–284)
      - Electrical sepias (in reverse), undated (Box 285)
      - Field orders, 1960, 1961, 1965 (Box 273, Folder 909)
      - Furnishings (Box 286)
      - Furnishings, additional (Box 287)
      - Miscellaneous oversize plans, sections, perspectives, 1956, 1960, undated (Box 287–320)
      - Plumbing sepias and as-builts, undated (Box 321)
      - Ramp house extensions (#5603-X), undated (Box 322)
      - Ramp house sketches, undated (Box 323)
    - Graphics
      - Baggage systems diagrams, undated (Box 324–328)
      - Layout studies for driveway signs, undated (Box 329, Folder 910)
      - Parking signs [used in mock-up], undated (Box 672, Folder 28)
      - Presentation of TWA logo and New York Airways helicopter sign variations, undated (Folder 689A–689B)
      - Univers alphabet for TWA roadway signs, undated (Box 329, Folder 911)
      - Werner alphabet, undated (Box 329, Folder 912)
    - Interiors
      - Ambassadors' Club cocktail lounge materials samples, undated (Box 329, Folder 913)
      - Correspondence; list of suppliers; drawings, 1961-1965, undated (Box 329, Folder 914)
      - Furnishings specifications; color schedules, 1961-1965, undated (Box 329, Folder 915)
      - Grille material samples and correspondence, 1968 (Box 329, Folder 916)
    - Notes on TWA plaque, 1962 (Box 329, Folder 917)
    - Photographs
      - Aerial view of terminal from parking lot, undated (Box 683C, Folder 151)
      - Architectural drawings, 1959 (Box 329, Folder 918)
        - Additional material (Box 672, Folder 30)
      - Construction, 1960, undated (Box 329, Folder 919)
        - Additional material, part 1 (Box 672, Folder 29)
        - Additional material, part 2 (Box 676, Folder 88)
      - Exteriors, 1962, undated (Box 329, Folder 920)
        - Additional material, part 1 (Box 672, Folder 29)
        - Additional material, part 2 (Box 676, Folder 88)
      - Interiors, 1962, undated (Box 329, Folder 921)
        - Additional material, part 1 (Box 672, Folder 29)
        - Additional material, part 2 (Box 676, Folder 88)
      - Models, undated (Box 330, Folder 922)
        - Additional material (Box 672, Folder 30)
      - Multiple exposure images; light studies [taken by Baltazar Korab], undated (Box 330, Folder 923)
      - Negatives, [1959], undated (Box 330, Folder 924)
      - Proof sheets: Baltazar Korab, Dan Page, Charles Eames, Ezra Stoller [?], 1962, undated (Box 330, Folder 925)
      - Publicity binder, undated (Box 330, Folder 926)
      - Renderings, plans, floor sections [for brochure], undated (Box 672, Folder 31)
      - Site plans; floor plans, 1961, undated (Box 330, Folder 927)
      - Sketches and renderings, undated (Box 330, Folder 928)
      - Stoller, Ezra: photographic order forms, undated (Box 330, Folder 929)
    - Press materials
      - Annotated "Fact Sheet - Trans World Flight Center", [1962] (Box 330, Folder 930)
      - "Building for Public Use" statement, undated (Box 330, Folder 931)
      - "News from TWA" press packets, undated (Box 330, Folder 932)
      - Press releases: drafts and final, 1957, 1962, undated (Box 330, Folder 933)
      - TWA brochures and menu for ground-breaking ceremony lunch, 1959, undated (Box 330, Folder 934)
    - Slides
      - As-built exterior and interior, undated (Box 330, Folder 935)
      - Construction, undated (Box 330, Folder 936)
      - Exhibit model, 1959, undated (Box 330, Folder 937)
      - Graphics, undated (Box 330, Folder 938)
      - Models
        - Interiors, undated (Box 330, Folder 939)
        - Tunnels, undated (Box 330, Folder 940)
    - Specifications
      - Barbershop, 1963 (Box 331, Folder 941)
      - Bulletins, 1959-1961 (Box 331, Folder 942)
      - Exterior and interior color schedules, 1961 (Box 331, Folder 943)
      - General conditions and architectural, 1959 (Box 331, Folder 944)
      - Heating, ventilating and air conditioning; plumbing, electrical, 1959 (Box 331, Folder 945)
  - Job 5604: International Business Machines [IBM], Rochester, MN
    Located on a flat 397-acre site that was formerly farmland, this sprawling 100,000-square-foot building, based on a four-foot module, is composed of a series of one- and two-story volumes surrounding two fully bounded courtyards and two entrance courts that opened on to parking lots set in extensive lawns. The one-story volume located at the core of the facility contains a cafeteria and employee lounges. The other one-story volumes, most of which were 250 by 250 feet in plan, contain 60,000 square feet of manufacturing facilities, while the two-story blocks, each 80 by 250 feet, house 40,000 square feet of office space. This distribution was based on the findings of IBM researchers that indicate manufacturing required one and a half times the amount of space as administration. The building is clad in porcelain-enameled aluminum panels developed by Saarinen's partner John Dinkeloo. The mass-produced three-ply panels, 5/16 inch thick and 4 feet wide, incorporate insulating asbestos-cement cores. Extending to a height of eight feet, the panels are stabilized laterally by aluminum mullions; there are no muntins. Neoprene gaskets seal the panels, which are striped in two tones of blue. Documentation on graphics for this project overlaps slightly with Saarinen's other IBM project, the Thomas J. Watson Research Center in Yorktown. Job 6204 pertains to specifications for an addition to the building.
    - Clippings, 1958, undated (Box 331, Folder 946)
      - Additional material (Box 672, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence: publicity and press, 1958-1962 (Box 331, Folder 947)
    - Drawings
      - As-built sepias, undated (Box 332)
      - Architectural sepias, undated (Box 333–335)
      - Detail sheets and miscellaneous furnishings, undated (Box 336)
      - Electrical sepias, undated (Box 337–338)
      - Mechanical diagrams and details; drinking fountain; section through concrete walks [from box 336], 1957, 1958, 1962 (Box 331, Folder 948)
      - Mechanical sepias, undated (Box 339–341)
      - Miscellaneous drawings, undated (Box 342)
      - Proposed addition, undated (Box 343)
      - Structural sepias, undated (Box 344)
    - Photographs
      - Exteriors; interiors, 1960, undated (Box 331, Folder 949)
        - Additional material (Box 672, Folder 33)
      - Models, undated (Box 331, Folder 950)
      - Negatives and transparencies, undated (Box 331, Folder 951)
      - Publicity binder, undated (Box 331, Folder 952)
      - Renderings, 1956, undated (Box 331, Folder 953)
      - Site plans; floor plans; structural detail, undated (Box 331, Folder 954)
    - Presentation: Building 2, Three Floors and Basement Mechanicals Plan, undated (Folder 690E)
    - Slides
      - Exteriors, 1958, undated (Box 345, Folder 955)
      - Graphics, model and construction, undated (Box 345, Folder 956)
      - Interiors, 1958, undated (Box 345, Folder 957)
    - Specifications
      - Bidding documents; general construction contract, 1956 (Box 345, Folder 958)
      - Bulletins #1 - #24, 1956-1957 (Box 345, Folder 959)
      - Bulletins #25 - #50 [missing #28], 1957 (Box 345, Folder 960)
      - Bulletins #51 - #64 [missing #61 - #63], 1957-1958 (Box 345, Folder 961)
      - Food service equipment, 1957 (Box 345, Folder 962)
      - Foundation piling and concrete work, 1956 (Box 345, Folder 963)
      - Main plant, 1957 (Box 345, Folder 964)
      - Outline specifications for manufacturing plant, 1957-1958 (Box 345, Folder 965)
      - Power house, 1956 (Box 345, Folder 966)
      - Proposed addition to plant soil exploration, 1962 (Box 345, Folder 967)
      - Site preparation, 1956 (Box 346, Folder 968)
      - Soil test borings, 1956 (Box 346, Folder 969)
      - Structural steel, 1956 (Box 346, Folder 970)
      - Warehouse, 1956 (Box 346, Folder 973 - 974)
  - Jobs 5604, 5606: International Business Machines [IBM], Rochester, MN and Yorktown, NY: Graphics
    - Drawings for signs, 1960-1961, undated (Box 346, Folder 973)
    - Photostats of signs, undated (Box 346, Folder 974)
    - Room signs, undated (Box 678, Folder 114)
    - Sign studies, undated (Box 346, Folder 975)
    - Typeface and color samples for office signs, undated (Box 346, Folder 976)
  - Job 5606: International Business Machines [IBM], Yorktown, NY: Thomas J. Watson Research Center
    The Thomas J. Watson Research Center, Saarinen's second IBM commission, is located on a generously sized property about a one-hour drive north of New York City. Approached by a long, curving road, the building describes a 1,090-foot arc along a ridge, its front facade glazed in reflective glass with a cantilevered concrete canopy marking the entrance, which is also highlighted by Seymour Lipton's abstract sculptures. Concrete bridges connect the building to its raised parking lot, spanning a Japanese-inspired garden designed by Sasaki, Walker, and Associates. Inside, Saarinen devised three stories of double-loaded corridors, windowless labs on one side, windowless offices on the other, which fan out along the curve. Views are reserved for the front hall, which extends the length of the entire arc like a promenade.
    Additional documentation for this project overlaps slightly with Saarinen's other IBM project in Rochester, Minnesota: the two buildings shared graphics and as such are listed in the finding aid together as Job 5604, 5606. Job 6308 consists of drawings for proposed radioisotope lab addition.
    - Brochures
      - Loose pages and illustrations, undated (Box 672, Folder 34)
      - "The New IBM Research Center in Yorktown, NY", [1959] (Box 346, Folder 977)
    - Clippings, 1961, 1977, undated (Box 346, Folder 978)
    - Correspondence: publicity and press, 1959-1962 (Box 346, Folder 981 - 982)
    - Drawings
      - Architectural fitting-up tracings, undated (Box 347)
      - Architectural record sepias, undated (Box 348–349)
      - Electrical fitting-up, undated (Box 350)
      - Electrical sepias (latest issue), undated (Box 351)
      - Graphics; space requirements, undated (Box 352)
      - HVAC fitting-up, undated (Box 353)
      - HVAC sepias (latest issue), undated (Box 354)
      - Miscellaneous drawings, undated (Box 355)
      - Oversize drawings on board, undated (Box 356–363)
      - Plumbing fitting-up; food service equipment (latest issue); landscape work (latest issue), undated (Box 364)
      - Plumbing sepias, undated (Box 365)
      - Presentation drawings, 1958 (Box 366)
      - Site development, undated (Box 367)
      - Site plan with plant list, undated (Box 368)
      - Sketches, undated (Box 369)
      - Sketches, first version, undated (Box 346, Folder 981)
    - Graphics
      - "Architectural Procedures"; document, 1961 (Box 346, Folder 982)
      - Correspondence and alphabet samples, 1958-1960 (Box 346, Folder 983)
      - Exit sign lettering, 1960 (Box 676, Folder 89)
      - Name plates; entry signs, 1960, undated (Box 674, Folder 65)
    - Interiors: material samples, 1959 (Box 346, Folder 984)
    - Interiors: material samples, 1959-1961 (Box 370, Folder 985)
    - Photographs
      - Aerial view of building, undated (Box 685B)
      - Construction, 1960, undated (Box 370, Folder 986)
      - Cserna, George proof sheets, undated (Box 370, Folder 987)
      - Exteriors, undated (Box 370, Folder 988)
        - Additional material, part 1 (Box 672, Folder 35)
        - Additional material, part 2 (Box 676, Folder 90)
      - Interiors, undated (Box 370, Folder 989)
        - Additional material, part 1 (Box 672, Folder 35)
        - Additional material, part 2 (Box 676, Folder 90)
      - Lipton, Seymour sculptures: "Argonaut #1" and "Argonaut #2", undated (Box 370, Folder 990)
      - Models: early, final, interiors, undated (Box 370, Folder 991)
      - Negatives and transparencies, undated (Box 370, Folder 992)
      - Publicity binder, undated (Box 370, Folder 993)
      - Rendering, undated (Box 370, Folder 994)
      - Site plans; floor plans, undated (Box 370, Folder 995)
      - Stoller, Ezra proof sheets, undated (Box 370, Folder 996)
    - Slides
      - Construction, 1960, undated (Box 371, Folder 997)
      - Exteriors, 1961, undated (Box 371, Folder 998)
      - Interiors, undated (Box 371, Folder 999)
      - Models
        - Early scheme and area planning, undated (Box 371, Folder 1000)
        - Final model: exteriors, undated (Box 371, Folder 1001)
        - Final model: interiors and render-collages, undated (Box 371, Folder 1002)
        - Site and mock-up, 1959, 1960, undated (Box 371, Folder 1003)
    - Specifications
      - Electrical work, 1959 (Box 371, Folder 1004)
      - General construction, 1959 (Box 371, Folder 1007 - 1008)
      - General construction addenda, 1959 (Box 371, Folder 1007)
      - General construction bulletins #101 - #137 [missing #125], 1959 (Box 371, Folder 1008)
      - General construction bulletins #138 - #164 [missing #162], 1960 (Box 371, Folder 1009)
      - General construction bulletins #165 - #199 [missing #179], 1960-1961 (Box 371, Folder 1010)
      - Heating, ventilating, and air conditioning, 1959 (Box 372, Folder 1011)
      - Inspection service contract, 1958 (Box 372, Folder 1012)
      - Plumbing, 1959 (Box 372, Folder 1013)
      - Proposed lake study, 1959 (Box 372, Folder 1014)
      - Radio Tracer Laboratory addition, 1963 (Box 372, Folder 1015)
      - Reinforcing steel contract, 1959 (Box 372, Folder 1016)
      - Sitework, 1958-1960 (Box 372, Folder 1017)
      - Test borings, 1959 (Box 372, Folder 1018)
  - Job 5607: General Motors Technical Center, Warren, MI: Basement kitchen for Styling Studios and Shop Building: Specifications, bulletins #1 - #10 [missing bulletins #7, #9], 1956-1957 (Box 372, Folder 1021 - 1023)
  - Job 5608: Yale University, New Haven, CT: David S. Ingalls Hockey Rink
    The program for this building, located in a residential area north of Yale's historic campus, called for a 2,800-seat hockey rink that could be expanded to accommodate 5,000 people when used for other functions, such as graduation. The dominant feature of the building is a roof suspended on cables from a 333-foot spinelike reinforced concrete arch, which provides a 288-foot-long and 183-foot-wide column-free area underneath. The arch is braced laterally by three 1 3/4-inch steel cables on each side. These are anchored to the exterior concrete walls, which, in plan, follow the curves of the arch's profile; this curvature was also adopted for the outdoor parking areas and lawns. The arch features upward-curved cantilevers at each end. New Haven-based architect Douglas W. Orr served as associate architect on the project, and Severud, Elstad, Krueger Associates as the structural engineer. Photographic documentation of this project is extensive, including a set of dated construction photographs, but only three architectural drawings exist for the project.
    - Clippings
      - English language publications, 1957-1958, 1984 (Box 372, Folder 1022)
      - Foreign language publications, 1958, 1960, undated (Box 372, Folder 1023)
      - L'Architecture d'Aujourd'hui, no. 85, undated (Box 672, Folder 36)
      - Yale University publications, 1956-1957 (Box 372, Folder 1024)
    - Correspondence: publicity and press, 1958-1962 (Box 373, Folder 1027 - 1029)
    - Drawings
      - Architectural plans, undated (Box 374, Box 374A–374C)
      - Rendering of interior, undated (Folder 375)
      - Sketches, undated (Box 373, Folder 1028)
    - Photographs
      - Construction, 1957-1958 (Box 373, Folder 1029)
        - Additional material (Box 672, Folder 37)
      - Exteriors, 1959-1962 (Box 373, Folder 1030)
      - Interiors, 1959, 1987, undated (Box 373, Folder 1031)
      - Models, [1956] (Box 373, Folder 1032)
        - Model (Folder 685C)
      - Negatives, undated (Box 373, Folder 1033)
      - Rendering, undated (Box 373, Folder 1034)
      - Sculpture above entrance, 1958, undated (Box 373, Folder 1035)
      - Site plans; floor plans; sections, 1956 (Box 373, Folder 1036)
      - Sketches for dome, undated (Box 373, Folder 1037)
      - Stoller, Ezra
        - Mounted prints, undated (Box 678, Folder 115)
        - Proof sheets (Box 373, Folder 1038)
    - Press release from Yale University, 1956 (Box 373, Folder 1039)
    - Slides
      - Construction, 1958, undated (Box 373, Folder 1040)
      - Exterior and interior, 1959, undated (Box 373, Folder 1041)
      - Graphics, model and roof, 1959, undated (Box 373, Folder 1042)
    - Specifications, 1957-1958 (Box 373, Folder 1043)
  - Job 5609: John Deere and Company Administrative Center, Moline, IL
    This 350,000-square-foot headquarters for a manufacturer of farm, construction, and lawn equipment is approached along a curving road that leads to a double-height display pavilion, 210 feet long by 35 feet high, that showcases a 100-foot-long three-dimensional mural, designed by Alexander Girard, made of 2,000 Deere artifacts. A glass-enclosed bridge connects this pavilion to the fourth floor of the seven-story glass-walled main administration building, which spans a ravine with two man-made lakes at its lowest point. Cor-Ten steel, in its first architectural use, was employed for columns, beams, sunscreens, and railings. A lower floor, partially below the level of the lake, contains an executive dining room with windows providing water-level views. Furniture designed by the Saarinen office was used throughout the interiors. Sasaki, Walker, and Associates were the project's landscape architects. Records for another building, #2, are listed as Job number 6402.
    Documentation for this project is extensive and includes several brochures produced by Deere for the opening ceremonies for the new building.
    - Area planning and site plans, 1956, undated (Box 376, Folder 1044)
    - Brochures
      - "Challenge to an Architect", 1964 (Box 376, Folder 1045)
      - Company handbooks and fliers, undated (Box 376, Folder 1046)
      - Program and invitation to opening, 1964 (Box 376, Folder 1047)
      - "Reflections of an Era", by John A. Kouwenhoven, undated (Box 376, Folder 1048)
      - "The Story of John Deere", undated (Box 376, Folder 1049)
    - Clippings, 1961-1983 (Box 376, Folder 1052 - 1053)
      - Additional material, part 1 (Box 673, Folder 40)
      - Additional material, part 2 (Box 673, Folder 44)
    - Correspondence: publicity and press, 1959-1965 (Box 376, Folder 1052)
    - Drawings
      - Architectural mylars
        - Building #1, undated (Box 377–378)
        - Building #2, undated (Box 379)
        - Building #3, building #4, undated (Box 380)
      - Architectural mylars connecting bridges; service station: architectural mylars, structural, electrical, mechanical sepias; architectural sepias, final, undated (Box 381)
      - "As-built" sketch drawings, undated (Box 382–383)
      - Carpet layouts; moving-in drawings; miscellaneous drawings, undated (Box 384)
      - Electrical sepias, undated (Box 385)
      - Equipment and movable partitions mylars, undated (Box 386)
      - Furnishings mylars, undated (Box 387–388)
      - Landscape: Sasaki, Walker and Associates, undated (Box 376, Folder 1053)
      - Landscaping mylars; "as-built" signs and graphics, undated (Box 389)
      - Metal office furniture mylars; fixed furniture design tracings; miscellaneous mylars, undated (Box 390)
      - Miscellaneous sketch drawings, 1959, undated (Box 391)
        Contains John Deere & Company Headquarters: early sketch
      - Mock-up building mylars; food service mylars; miscellaneous utilities requirement sepias, undated (Box 392)
      - Record sepias
        - Mechanical, undated (Box 393)
        - Yard and plumbing, undated (Box 394)
      - Site mylars; original site record sepias, undated (Box 395)
      - Site survey material; topographical survey, undated (Box 396)
      - Structural sepias, undated (Box 397)
      - Wardrobe notes; maintenance office, undated (Box 376, Folder 1054)
    - Graphics
      - Aisle marker; room identifier; floor directories; menu board; sign placement maps, undated (Box 674, Folder 66)
      - Ampersand studies, undated (Box 376, Folder 1055)
      - Correspondence and notes on signs, 1962-1964 (Box 376, Folder 1056)
      - Deere alphabet samples [various sizes], undated (Box 376, Folder 1057)
      - Directory and plaque studies and mock-up, undated (Box 376, Folder 1058)
      - Directory signs; pin oak plaque; DEERE letters, undated (Box 681, Folder 137)
      - Exterior directional and traffic sign studies, undated (Box 376, Folder 1059)
      - Exterior door studies, undated (Box 376, Folder 1060)